Guide to the Charles Robert Leslie Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Correspondence, Series III
  - Harriet Stone Leslie
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Sunday Eve"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and blue/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Harriet writes perhaps from the train, noting at the top of her letter that "The rail road is very long and tedious." She says that it is cool on this particular evening. She mentions a "Mrs. Beales & Mrs. M. & the babies" who have recently arrived and remarks on the strength of Mrs. M. She inquires about Harriet and George and hopes that "the girls will...look into the kitchen without appearing to seek for faults." She insists that Robert come down to stay with her, after Mrs. Beales has requested his presence. Harriet hesitates to have the girls join her in town, however, as they are "very particular." She worries about Mary's eye, which bothers her a great deal and seems infected. She closes on a more positive note, commenting on the pleasant weather and the moonlight on the water, which is "quite the color of your black & gold fish."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Tuesday Morning"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 11.2 x 19 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Harriet writes about the date of her upcoming return home, saying that Leslie may either come up and join them for a night or that she can get the children home herself. She wishes, with underlining for emphasis, "to be with you alone at Hampton Court..." She goes on to discuss hiring a new maid and remarks that Miss Moore (a local acquaintance) has "read some of 'the Life,' presumably one of the autobiographical or biographical projects on which Leslie was working. Harriet closes with a fanciful discussion of the pleasures and possible excesses of living in the country.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Monday Evening"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 13.5 x 18 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Harriet writes to follow up on her daughter Harriet's note to Charles. Harriet Jane Leslie requested money from her father, for the family, but Harriet Stone writes that they probably will not need as much as her daughter requested. She comments on the pleasant weather and remarks that Mary's drawings are very lifelike and impressive. She lists a few things that they have purchased, including parasols, flannel for petticoats, and boots, as a way of illustrating that they are not "extravagant." She sends love to a family member (perhaps the "Aunt C." whose train ticket to Brighton Harriet has purchased) and sends her love to "my Buck" and "dear Brad."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Saturday"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Harriet writes mournfully about Charles's lonely situation without the family and hopes earnestly that he will come to be with them. She reports that Robert has arrived safely. She goes on to say that she will be happy "on Monday because I shall know you will be enjoying yourself..." with some mutual friends. She closes and then writes a second note to say that the sleeping arrangements are satisfactory and that Charles can join them comfortably. She hopes that "Rebecca will come up" to visit Charles and asks him to make up his mind about staying at "Aberdeen Place" or else she will come home to him. She passes along instructions for Susan, the servant, and then reports on Robert, Bradford, and George going rambling and painting. She closes with a few domestic details.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 2 pages (1 leaf); 18.2 x 11.5 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Harriet writes to report her safe arrival and that she has seen a Miss Julia Moore, who took her to the Moore home. She asks Charles to "give [her] love to the army at home" and comments on "the commander of the Theatre," who is perhaps one of the children. She closes with a cryptic postscript saying, "The little lady lived at Kingston."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Tuesday, 29th October"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.5 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Harriet writes from Brighton. She acknowledges receipt of 15 pounds from Leslie, and reports on the improving health of Caroline. Harriet is content in Brighton, but misses her husband. She comments a bit on money matters and moves on to praise Bradford for being "such an excellent good fellow," saying that she will be sorry to part with him. She adds a postscript about George wanting another waistcoat and gives Leslie directions to a shop where he might find one for a certain price.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "17th Thursday"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 2 pages (1 leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Harriet writes while away from home, telling her husband that she noticed one of his pictures, "May Day," as being put up for sale along with other items belonging to a gentleman. Harriet comments on a Mrs. Dunlop, who left her goddaughter a considerable amount of money. She says that the day is lovely and she misses her loved ones, though she knows that Leslie is well "& in fresh air." She laments feeling that she is "doing nothing for my Family at home." The letter continues past the extant pages.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Tuesday morning"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.5 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Harriet writes from Brighton. She complains that Charles has been inattentive to her letters and reminds him that their daughter Caroline has a cold. She says that they are comfortable in their lodgings with a Mrs. Mays_ard. Harriet continues to comment on Caroline's cold, pledging to get her better. She asks Leslie about a card for/from a Mrs. Bates, and mentions that she has seen the Rogerses. Harriet frets about the state of things at home and advises Leslie to buy for himself, Bradford, and George, "some of the warm trousers all the fashion now..." She closes by stating, "I know of no sea like the Brighton Sea."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Wednesday 16"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 3 pages (1 folded leaf); 15.2 x 19 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Harriet hopes that Charles has arrived safely, presumably back at home after dropping off the family on a holiday. She says that they have " a nice little bed for Brad" but goes on to complain that "our bedroom was so much infested last night with the smell..." Harriet remarks that the family felt lost without Leslie there, and that Bradford "was up this morning & over the Downs," suggesting that this letter comes from Sussex. She frets about Bradford's health, suspecting something is wrong with him because "he breathes so hard at times & seems tired without cause..." She closes with a note about a Miss Wadding who has returned with them and sends her love to Caroline.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s "Wednesday"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 3 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Harriet writes that she received Charles's last letter. She writes that she grieves "over Mrs. Knott," but says that the dead woman was such a good Christian that no one should be too upset because she is going to Heaven. She reports that Mr. Wallis has lent his punt, but that Robert enjoys nothing more than sketching. She believes that Robert should go "to Carey's school & make him drudge well there for a year at least." She comments on the marriage of Mrs. Knott's niece, but says that "Alfred C. I am sure wonders any one should get married," as he feels that pretty girls are suited only for artist's models and that "children [are]...useless." She sends instructions for the servant, Susan, and asks Charles to bring Caroline's boots when he arrives in town.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s "Saturday"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 15.5. x 20 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Harriet writes, complaining about the scant postal service. She hopes that Charles is well and remarks on the pleasant weather. She writes about looking for a house to rent while she and the children are away. She comments on the price of a copyright (she says it should be 50 pounds), possibly referring to a matter with an engraver that is mentioned in another letter. She sends a playful remonstrance to Caroline and asks Charles to kiss "the dear Buck," likely referring to one of their sons, but to tell him that "he must be industrious." Harriet mentions an Uncle Sam and his wife, with whom they are staying. She calls Uncle Sam's wife "a regular Irish rogue."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 3 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Harriet writes, in typical fashion, expressing worries about home while away. She asks Leslie and their son Robert to write and tell her more about what is going on at home. She notes that Caroline has told her of a "little sweeper girl" who "rings the bell very often," and asks Leslie to have a servant, Amelia, warn the girl and then report her to the police. She hopes that George's Sunday clothes will be readied for church and closes, perhaps unintentionally comically, "your lovely wife, Harriet Leslie." A postscript reports that a Mrs. Stone is going to visit a Mr. Armstrong and is very proud of the fact; although Harriet has already had a call from him, she has not informed Mrs. Stone.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 2 pages (1 leaf); 18 x 11.5 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Harriet writes a brief letter to tell Charles that it is too late in the season and too much work to take Caroline to Mr. Forsters. She asks Caroline to wait until Charles returns before they "engage any thing."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Wednesday June 2nd"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 2 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and blue ink. (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Harriet complains that her landlady is "a regular gripe all" and announces that she will be coming home the following day. She reports that a Mrs. B. (perhaps the Mrs. Beale referred to in other letters from the seaside) wished her and the children to stay but that Mary's eye continues to trouble her and she does not want to be away from home. She closes with information about her travel plans for returning home, telling Charles that she will be on a train passing through Brighton and arriving "in town at 5.30 that is 1/2 past 5 o'cl in town."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.5 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Harriet acknowledges receipt of Leslie's recent letter and "the Punch with your Sir Roger in it..." referring to a print of his painting, "Sir Roger De Coverley Going to Church." She comments on the sermon preached at church earlier in the day. She remarks that "none but a man impressed with the transitoryness [sic] of this life could have preach [sic] such a sermon..." Rather humorously, she notes that, given the potentially fatal heart complaint she knows the preacher to have, "all Parsons ought to have heart complaints" that they might preach as effectively. She closes with affectionate messages for their sons, "dear Buck and Rob," and a couple of other comments.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.2 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Harriet writes from "Standwell House, Rottingdean." She expresses dismay not to have had a letter from Charles, and hopes that he is well. She asks for George to bring senna leaves from home and reports on Harriet, Caroline, and Mary all bathing earlier in the day, saying that she wishes she had the courage to do it too. She has watched a storm all night, wondering whether Charles experienced it too. She admonishes Charles again for not writing and states that she is anxious about him and wishes she hadn't left him. She is pleased with the food and wishes she could share it with Charles. She warns him not to stay in Robert's room because it is too cold and damp, again wishing that Charles were with her to experience the warm and pleasant weather. Bradford has befriended a local couple called the Coppers, and will "paint them another picture." Harriet requests a board for him, "like Mary's" and follows with a list of tasks for the servant Susan to perform.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 2pages (1 leaf); 11 x 9.2 cm. Fragment of autograph letter, not signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 37)
      A portion of a longer letter to Charles, which appears to have been torn or separated as a loose page, from the rest of the letter. The fragment begins mid-sentence, with Harriet writing about a handsome woman, who with her spouse, has paid a visit to Cholmleys. She writes of her longing to see Charles and then advises him that their daughter, Harriet, "need not mention our friends here to little Buck." She also advises Charles not to pay for Rebecca's train fare.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 2 pages (1 folded leaf); 13.5 x 18 cm. Fragment of autograph letter, not signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 38)
      An apparent fragment of a letter, in which Harriet writes about a Miss Doyle, of whom she approves "for the Girls." She writes that "Captain gives a sorry account of the Major Leslie, I mean the Mrs..." and goes on to quote a woman complaining about the inferiority of London. Perhaps she refers to C.R. Leslie's brother, Capt. Thomas Jefferson Leslie, who had had a distinguished career with the U.S. Army.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1850 October 1; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 20 x 25 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Harriet writes from 2 Abercorn Place, St. John's Wood. She pens a brief note about items forgotten, including a sketchbook and drawing materials. She says that she will send the package of things (presumably to Charles) if "Thomas says it is of consequence enough." She sends her love to the friends with whom Charles is staying. The letter is addressed to Charles at the home of Edmund Beale, 42 Rue de Constantine, Boulougne.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1850 October 7; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 2 pages (1 folded leaf); 20 x 25 cm. Autograph letter, unsigned; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Harriet writes to Charles in Paris, having sent a previous letter that was misdirected. She comments on wanting "to get Caroline away," most likely to school, soon, and asks Charles not to leave "M. with the Beales unless she can have a room to herself." Perhaps she refers to their daughter Mary. Harriet goes on to express her dislike and distrust of someone (the line is partially crossed out) and says that "she keeps you in hot water & wants angels to bear all her tartness..." She sends love to Mary and asks Charles to advise her not to spend a lot of money on a bonnet but to buy indoor shoes instead. The letter ends with Harriet's comment that "all we want is for you to take care of yourself." It is not clear whether this was the closing of the letter, but there are no other pages. The letter is addressed to Leslie at the Hotel Wagnam, Rue de Rivoli, Paris.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1850, "Sunday October 9th"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 20 x 25 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Letter is addressed to Leslie at the Hotel des Tuileries in Paris. Harriet reports that a Mr. and Mrs. Redgrave have just arrived and told her that someone (perhaps their son) was married and had just arrived from Paris with his new wife, "a Miss Wright." She jokes, cryptically, that it's "better late [than never]." Harriet comments that Caroline's health is improving and that she misses her husband, who seems to be traveling with their daughter, Mary. Harriet issues various instructions, including some on Leslie's washing (she suggests that he not wash too much) and that he have Polly, a servant, look after him. She tells him strongly not to go to Beales again, and writes that Bradford can come to get Mary at Folkestone. Harriet bemoans the fact that "taste is flown the land" as "Hazlewood has yellowed all the windows in the Church, all mustard, a November fog." She tells Charles to pack up his own things and to have Mary remember to take her best things and look after her father's belongings.
  - Mary Leslie
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, circa 1840-1845; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 1 page (1 leaf); 17.5 x 11 cm. Fragment of an autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink with pen and ink illustration. (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Mary Leslie writes to her father to tell him that she has had "three dips in the sea" and adds a few other details about an apparent seaside trip. She includes a small sketch at the top of the letter, saying "I drew the little chur[ch] this morning..." The tone and handwriting of this letter suggest that it was written when Mary was still quite young.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Harriet Stone Leslie, circa 1845-1850; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.2 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink, with graphite sketch and embellishments. (Box 1, Folder 43)
      In this undated letter, Mary writes to her mother while on a visit, perhaps to relatives. She includes a graphite sketch of a mother with two children, indicating that they are part of the Mason family. She says that the last time she was "here," the eldest child was the "little boy I drew" but has now grown big. She reports that "we are enjoying ourselves very much..." She discusses a hunting excursion on donkeys, and asks her mother not to worry about sending her paint box to her, as it is "too late in the year to sketch out of doors." Mary writes that a neighbor, Mrs. Allen, gave them some jam and loaned them books, of which Felicia Heman's poetry was meant for her. Mary's tone and handwriting suggest that she was a young teenager at the time of this letter.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1851 or 1852, June 9; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink with watercolor illustration. (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Mary writes while visiting Bradford in Chepstow, Wales. She reports that "Braddy" has taken her to "Beachley, where there is a long pier reaching out into the river..." She says that there is to be a flower show at "the castle" in the next week, and anticipates a visit to the show, when Bradford will "have a holyday." She writes of drawing flowers, amply supplied by "the Miss Phillips," and of sketching "Miss Kinbys garden." Mary writes of an odd parlor trick or prank played by a lady in the area who drew a baby's face on her hand and convinced a child that it was "a dead baby, and when the little girl took it, and found it moved, she was quite frightened and ran away, but when she found it was only a hand, she wanted to make one...and went upstairs to frighten the nurse." Mary illustrates the letter with a charming watercolor vignette of a red squirrel by the side of a pond, saying that she and Bradford saw a similar scene on their way home.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1851 or 1852; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 11.2 x 18 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink and with a watercolor illustration. (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Mary writes a short note to thank her father for money that he sent, saying that it was lucky that he addressed it to her and not to Bradford, as he was "at the bridge" and unavailable. As part of a five year apprenticeship to Isambard Brunel, Bradford was working, in 1851 and 1852, an assistant engineer at Chepstow Bridge; it is likely that the mention of him being at the bridge refers to this post. She includes a sketch of "the Castle as it appeared yesterday from Tutshill during the Flower Show." She is glad to hear that C.R. Leslie and his wife are thinking of coming to visit Mary and Bradford and reports that despite the pouring rain, she is still not ready to come home yet.
    - Letter to Harriet Stone Leslie, probably 1851 or 1852, July 15; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink with watercolor illustration. (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Mary writes to her mother, sending the letter with Bradford as he heads home for a visit. Mary reports on a recent event (perhaps the opening) at the Chepstow Bridge, saying that it "looked beautiful all decorated with flags, I was just in time to see the first engine driven across..." She asks her mother to send along a "blue band," part of a dress that she has received from home, but whose "defect" can only be concealed with the missing band. She comments on the pleasant "bauuing" of the sheep and lambs outside her window at night. She includes an unfinished watercolor of a verdant riverbank with a bridge across it.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1851 or 1852, July 18; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, illustrated and signed; written in pen and brown/black ink with watercolor and pen and ink illustration. (Box 1, Folder 47)